原视频名：Why It's So Hard To Predict Where סִינִית Latest Piece Of Space Junk Will Land
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/afGFmAljL5E
原视频发布日期：20210508
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
Once again a big chunk of סִינִית space junk is on its way back to earth.
一大块太空垃圾又一次在返回地球的路上
Now this is not an altogether uncommon occurrence
现在 这并不是一个完全不常见的情况
来源似乎是b23.tv/av18228412，2017-11-05 19:45 XC LC-2 CZ-3B Y46 BeiDou-3 M1/M2，
助推器残骸落于百色市田林县境内
because חרסינה has something of a reputation for
因为把用完的助推器 扔到靠近人们居住的地方 也是出现过的情况
dropping spent booster stages from rockets that come from its inland sites near to or on places where people live
but this is different.
但这次的不太一样
This is a 23 ton core stage from the largest rocket they have
这是一枚其最大火箭的芯级 质量有23吨
which is currently in orbit around the earth
目前正在地球轨道上运行
and could fall back to earth practically anywhere
而且几乎可以落到地球的任何地方
and we're not even sure of the time or place.
而且我们甚至不确定时间和地点
So this is the core from the ארוך הב במרץ
那么 这是来自ארוך הב במרץ的芯级
and believe it or not we had this exact same problem
同时信不信由你 在上次使用该火箭时也遇到了同样的问题
the last time they used the rocket in 2020.
也就是2020年的时候
ארוך ה במרץ is the biggest rocket חרסינה has.
ארוך ה במרץ是其拥有的最大的火箭
It's a top-tier launch vehicle comparable to the Proton, Delta IV, Ariane 5 or Falcon 9.
这是一枚顶级的运载火箭 可与质子号 德尔塔四号(重型) 阿丽亚娜五号或猎鹰九号相比
It's got a fully cryogenic core using liquid oxygen and hydrogen
芯级使用完全低温的推进剂 也就是液氢液氧
and it has four strap-on boosters that burn kerosene and liquid oxygen to get high thrust for launch.
它有四个捆绑式助推器 燃烧煤油和液氧以获得发射(起飞)时所需的高推力
There's a second stage that sits on top of this that uses liquid hydrogen and oxygen
在此之上还有一个使用液氢液氧推进剂的二级
but the הב doesn't actually use this.
但ארוך הב במרץ实际上并没有二级
It skips that and puts the payload directly on the core stage
二级被去掉了 芯级上面直接搭载有效载荷
and that's why that giant core has been left in orbit after putting the ה טיאנה module up into orbit.
而这就是为什么在ה טיאנה入轨后 巨大的芯级会留在轨道上
So yeah it's about 23 tons we think.
所以是的 我们认为它大约有23吨
And you would think they could bring it back right.
你会认为他们可以把它带回来 对吧
Well during the live stream according to some סִינִית speaking fans I have
那么 在直播过程中 根据我的一些סִינִית粉丝的说法
there were some comments about deorbiting this stage according to the commentators.
根据节目中评论员的说法 芯级会进行离轨
But if that was actually the plan then it must have gone wrong
但如果这真的是计划 那么它一定出了问题
or it might be the commentators just don't know what they're talking about
或者可能是评论员不知道他们在说什么
which is quite common to be honest.
不过说实话 这是很常见的
People on the ground observing the stage hours after it launched
地面上的人在它发射后几个小时观察了这个分级
showed that it was spinning and as of yesterday it was spinning at about 12 RPM.
显示 它正在旋转 而截至昨天 它的旋转速度约为12转/分(r/min)
And that is an object that's like 33 meters long or 100 feet long
而这是一个长约33米或100英尺的物体
and even video of the deployment showed that
甚至在ה טיאנה部署的视频中显示
it might have been rotating as the space station module receded from the upper stage the core stage let's say.
在空间站模块从上面级 或者说芯级分离的时候 其就一直在旋转了
Yeah we only have estimates of the mass by the way.
是的 顺便说一下 我们只有对质量的估计
Those are based on sort of סִינִית media reports
这些都是基于סִינִית媒体的一些报道
which state that it's 187 tons when full with 165 tons of propellant
其中指出 它在装满165吨推进剂时有187吨
so that's where 23 tons come from
那么这就是23吨的来源
and that's actually comparable to the module at launch but that's largely a coincidence.
这实际上与发射时的舱段质量相当 但这只是一个巧合
And importantly it's also about twice the mass of the Tiangong station
而且重要的是 它的质量也是טיאנגונג的两倍
which re-entered uncontrollably back in I think 2018.
我觉得是在2018年 它进行了无控再入
Now this booster is not the largest thing to return to earth in an uncontrolled fashion.
那么这个芯级不是以无控方式返回地球的最大物体
That dubious honor belongs to Skylab which was a 70 ton space station
这个不幸的荣誉属于天空实验室 这是一个70吨的空间站
and after a few crews had visited it they left it in orbit
而在一些乘员访问过它之后 他们把它留在了轨道上
with the plan that the Space Shuttle would be able to rendezvous with it and boost its orbit.
计划航天飞机将能够与它会合并提升其轨道
The problem was the Space Shuttle wasn't ready yet.
问题是航天飞机还没有准备好
And it took way longer to develop than they expected.
而且它的开发时间比预计的要长
By the time the Space Shuttle was even getting close
当航天飞机快完成的时候
Skylab was skimming through the upper atmosphere
天空实验室就已经擦过上层大气了
and threatening to fall anywhere in the planet.
并可能坠落到地球上的任何地方
So NASA did what it could.
那么NASA做了它能做的
It couldn't adjust the orbit because it didn't have propellant
它无法调整轨道 因为没有推进剂
but it could adjust the attitude and change the amount of drag that it was experienced
但可以调整姿态 改变其所经受的阻力大小
so they steered it as best they could and it ended up landing in Australia
所以他们尽可能地去控制它 最后在澳大利亚着陆了
which was probably fine
这可能是好的
because well the local wildlife was more dangerous than Skylab could be.
因为当地的野生动物比天空实验室更危险
But many people also forget that the second stage of the Saturn V that launched Skylab
但是很多人也忘记了发射天空实验室的土星五号的二级
that also stayed in orbit after it put the station into orbit
其在将空间站送入轨道后也留在了轨道上
and that meant that it was an uncontrolled object.
而这意味着它是一个不受控制的物体
S-II干质量36.2吨，来源en.wikipedia.org/wiki/S-II
It was about 30 tons
它有大约30吨
and it spent 18 months in orbit before just by luck it deorbited over the ocean
之后它在轨道上呆了18个月 然后幸运地在海洋上离轨(再入)了
and that is the largest fully uncontrolled re-entry.
那么这是最大的完全不受控制的再入
Now over on the Soviet Union side they actually mostly kept their Salyut stations under control for de-orbits
那么 在苏联方面 实际上大部分礼炮号空间站都进行了受控离轨(再入)
but in the case of Salyut 7 it was also boosted into a storage orbit
但在礼炮7号的情况下 其也被提升到一个存储轨道上
with the plan that the Soviet Shuttle the Buran would be able to boost its orbit
计划让苏联的暴风雪号航天飞机来提升它的轨道
and we all know that didn't work either.
而我们都知道那也没有成功
I mean Shuttle development is clearly not something to be making predictions about.
我是指 航天飞机的发展显然是难以进行预测的
When Salyut 7 re-entered it ended up being visible from Argentina
在礼炮七号再入时 在阿根廷可以看到它
but the debris probably ended up out in the ocean and nothing was to be found.
但碎片可能最终完全掉入海里 什么也没有找到
But anyway the vast majority of big pieces of hardware are well controlled.
但无论如何 绝大多数的大体积(空间)设备(再入)都得到了很好的控制
Like the 120 ton Mir space station which was so well controlled
就像重达120吨的和平号空间站 控制得非常好
that people were actually chartering flights to the landing zone
以至于实际上人们都包机前往坠落区
so they could watch this monster thing re-enter and burn up over the pacific.
这样他们就可以看到这个庞然大物的再入 同时在太平洋上空燃烧起来
某种程度上，即使是STS-51-L(挑战者号事故)和STS-107(哥伦比亚号事故)的外部储箱也得到了控制
And of course after Skylab NASA made sure to dispose of every single Space Shuttle external tank.
当然 在天空实验室之后 NASA确保每一艘航天飞机的外部储箱都被丢弃
早期型SWT干质量35吨左右，中期型LWT干质量30吨左右，后期型SLWT干质量26.5吨
来源en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Space_Shuttle_external_tank#Versions
Each of these was over 30 tons of inert mass.
每一个都是超过30吨的干质量
These were dropped by the Space Shuttle
这些都是由航天飞机投放的
and they were dropped such that it wasn't fully in orbit
而且投放时都并没有完全入轨
and its trajectory would ensure that when it was carried out and hit the atmosphere.
同时其弹道将确保离轨并再入大气层
It would be re-entering over the ocean.
(同时)其会在海洋上空再入
The Shuttle of course had to use its Orbital Maneuvering System
当然 航天飞机必须使用其轨道机动系统
to complete the orbital insertion to stay in space.
来完成入轨 这样才能保持在太空中
So yeah generally if anything large is being de-orbited in a destructive fashion
那么 没错 一般来说 如果有什么大型的东西以破坏性的方式脱离轨道的话
it's aimed so that it will re-enter in the middle of a convenient ocean.
会让它瞄准方便(弹道设计的)海洋的中间来再入
There's a point in the middle of the pacific where hundreds of satellites have been de-orbited
有数百颗卫星在太平洋中部的一个位置离轨
although most of them will burn up completely.
尽管它们中的大多数会被完全烧毁
So there's no like large chunks of space hardware littering the bottom of the pacific ocean to be found.
所以不会出现这样的情况 比如大块的太空设备丢弃在太平洋的底部被发现
So yeah this is the second time that חרסינה has flown this rocket
所以 这是חרסינה第二次发射这枚火箭了
and both times has resulted in an uncontrolled re-entry for that core
而这两次都导致了火箭芯级的失控再入
and it's I'm going to say it's pretty darn embarrassing that they lack the will to do this properly right.
而我想说的是 缺乏意愿来适当地做这件事会令人尴尬 对吧
I don't know what's wrong with them.
我不知道发生甚么事了
I hope they can fix their problem.
我希望这个问题能得到解决
So in may of 2020 the same booster design burned up over the Atlantic
那么 在2020年5月 同样的芯级设计 在大西洋上空烧毁了
and some debris did actually make it all the way downrange to Africa
而且一些碎片实际上一直沿着弹道方向落到了非洲
and a piece was found in the Ivory Coast
之后在科特迪瓦发现了一片残骸
which looked to me like some plumbing possibly an oxygen pipe.
在我看来这是一部分管道 可能是液氧管路的一部分
2021-03-04 08:24 KSC, LC-39A Falcon 9 B1049.8 Starlink v1.0 L17，
二级再入时间为2021-03-26
And to be fair recently we had a similar thing happen with a SpaceX second stage
而且公平地说 最近有一个类似的事情发生在SpaceX的二级上
where they wanted to perform the deorbit burn but it failed
他们想进行离轨点火 但是失败了
and it ended up deorbiting randomly and dropping debris over Washington State and Canada.
最终二级随机脱离轨道 并在(美国西海岸)华盛顿州和加拿大上空掉落碎片
截至2021-05-09，根据zarya.info，猎鹰9号二级受控再入失败的星链任务有，
Starlink v1.0 L4(www.zarya.info/Diaries/Launches/Launches.php?year=2020#012)，
Starlink v1.0 L12(www.zarya.info/Diaries/Launches/Launches.php?year=2020#070)，
Starlink v1.0 L17(www.zarya.info/Diaries/Launches/Launches.php?year=2021#017)，
共3次，占全部星链发射26次中的11.6%，同时根据www.spacelaunchreport.com/falcon9ft.html，猎鹰9号二级大概4.5吨干质量
And this is a very rare occurrence though
而这是一个(非常)罕见的情况 虽然
because they generally they're able to put these things down safely
因为他们通常能够安全地把这些东西带回地球
and yeah this is much smaller stage as well.
而且没错 猎鹰9号二级更小
I mean I wish I could tell you where this core would land.
我是指 我希望我可以告诉你这个芯级会在哪里坠落
Indeed you might think that since we can accurately predict orbits months ahead,
的确 你可能会认为 既然我们可以提前几个月准确地预测轨道
it should actually be pretty easy to figure this out right.
那么实际上应该很容易搞清楚这个问题 对吧
Newton's laws are simple right.
牛顿定律很简单对吧
But the thing is this is true for high orbits where the atmospheric drag has very little effect
但问题是 这对高轨来说是正确的 因为在那里大气阻力的影响很小
but lower down in the atmosphere this isn't the case.
但在较低的轨道 接触到大气层的地方 情况就不是这样了
The weak influence of the atmosphere
大气层的微弱影响
very quickly causes our orbits to diverge from our idealized calculations.
很快就导致轨道与理想化的计算相背离
Like in an ideal model the drag slows the satellite down
就像在一个理想的模型中 阻力使卫星慢了下来
which in response falls down to a lower orbit
结果就是 它落到一个较低的轨道上
and then paradoxically because it's in a lower orbit it actually has to go faster
然后自相矛盾的是 因为在一个较低的轨道上 实际上速度得变得更快
so the drag which is pushing to slow it down
所以推动它慢下来的阻力
actually results in the satellite moving faster in a lower orbit.
实际上导致了卫星在较低的轨道上移动得更快
It's confusing but that's orbital mechanics.
这很让人困惑 但这就是轨道力学
It's weird like that.
它就是这么奇怪
Also if the orbit is elliptical with a significant difference between the perigee and the apogee
另外 如果轨道是椭圆的 近地点和远地点之间速度会存在明显差异
then the high point the apogee will descend faster than the low point right.
那么远地点将比近地点的下降速度更快
It'll tend to get more circular over time.
随着时间的推移 它将倾向于变得更圆
But yeah eventually a decaying satellite gets so low
但是 是的 最终一个下落中的卫星(的高度)会变得如此之低
that it very quickly begins to lose altitude due to the drag.
以至于很快就会因为阻力而失去高度
The atmospheric density builds up
大气层的密度越来越大
and eventually the whole thing gets torn apart by aerodynamic forces and destroyed by atmospheric heating.
最终整个东西被空气动力撕碎 并被大气层加热而破坏
And a few bits of debris may make it to the ground.
还有一些碎片可能会扛下来 并落到地面上
But I'm going to say if you're seeing this thing flying overhead
但我要说的是 如果你看到这东西从头顶上飞过
you're probably safe from debris
你可能是安全的 不会被碎片砸到
because anything light enough to slow down and fall on you is going to burn up before then.
因为任何轻到可以减速并落在你身上的东西 都会在那之前烧光
It's the stuff that's going to survive that tends to move further downrange
能够扛下来的东西往往会沿弹道方向 向更远的地方移动
and so yeah worry about people downrange from you.
那么 是的 要担心那些处在沿弹道方向 更远位置的人们
But yeah predicting this decay is complicated further
但是 是的 预测这种轨道衰减会更加复杂
by the fact that the earth isn't a proper sphere.
因为地球并不是一个理想的球体
It's kind of lumpy.
其算是长满了各种块状的凸起
And the atmosphere actually is kind of lumpy too
而且实际上大气层也有点不稳定
and it changes over time as solar activity causes changes in the atmosphere.
而且会随着时间的推移而变化 因为太阳活动会导致大气层的变化
And there's no like really good measurements for how this changes like in real time.
对于这种变化的实时性 没有很好的测量方法
Like the best you can do is actually take a look at what's happening to your satellite
你能做的最好的事情就是看看你的卫星上发生了什么
and try to infer what the atmosphere is for the next pass.
并试图推断出下一次经过的大气层会是什么状态
And so yeah we're 24 hours out from the predicted entry time.
那么是的 我们离预测的再入时间还有24小时
And we still have error bars of plus or minus six hours.
而且我们仍然有正负6小时的误差
That's 12 hours.
那就是12个小时
That's ridiculous.
这种精度实在很荒唐
And in that 12 hours it's going to travel around the world eight times.
在这12个小时里 它要绕地球八圈
So there's no chance of figuring out what longer should land up at.
所以没有机会弄清楚到底在什么时间 在什么地方坠落
On the bright side because we know the inclination
从好的方面看 因为我们知道倾角
we know that it has to be south of 42 degrees north and north of 42 degrees south.
我们知道 它得在北纬42度以南和南纬42度以北
And so that rules out most of Europe, Canada, Russia.
所以这就排除了欧洲 加拿大和俄罗斯的大部分地区
They're all safe.
这些地区都是安全的
But a lot of the usa is still covered by that.
但是美国的很多地方仍然在这个范围内
The whole continent of Africa, most of the Americas
整个非洲大陆 美洲的大部分地区
Australia, New Zealand, Middle East, India and of course חרסינה are all inside this region.
澳大利亚 新西兰 中东 印度 当然还有חרסינה都在这个区域内
And don't worry because the odds of it ending up near you are staggeringly small.
而且不要担心 因为它落在你附近的几率小得惊人
And the odds of it landing in the ocean are about 70 percent.
同时它落入海洋的几率约为70%
And if we use that narrowed 12-hour window
而如果我们使用那个缩小的12小时的窗口
you can actually plot the orbit that you expected to take over that time
你实际上可以绘制出预计在那段时间内所使用的轨道
and it looks like South Africa is ruled out
而且看起来南非已经被排除在外了
and I don't think I'm going to see in California
同时我不认为我会在加利福尼亚看到
because we're right on the very edge of the far end of the window.
因为我们正好在窗口的最末端
But we've cut it down to half a day
但是我们已经把时间缩短到了半天
and we really haven't made much of a difference in the land area it could hit.
而且其可能坠落的土地面积并没有太大改变
So yeah over the weekend the precision should get better
因此 是的 在这周末 精度应该会得到改善
and maybe it will be visible for some people.
而且也许对一些人来说 它将是可见的
Maybe we will get some great pictures of this re-entry of this monster thing breaking up in the sky
也许我们会得到一些关于这个庞然大物在天空中碎裂 再入的伟大照片
which will be nice.
这将是很好的
And hopefully no one will get hurt.
而且希望没有人会受伤
But what would be really nice.
但真正好的是
It would be nice if חרסינה would fix the ארוך הב במרץ to bring it up to date with modern rockets
如果חרסינה能修复ארוך הב במרץ 使其变得更加现代化 那就更好了
and make it like a good orbital citizen.
并使其成为一个良好的轨道公民
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]